<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Sermon preached at the court at White Hall before the Kings Maiesty, vpon Sunday being the 13. of May 1604. By Anthony Rudd Professor of Diuinitie, and Bishop of Saint Dauids</title>
            <author>Rudd, Anthony, 1549 or 50-1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836744</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836744</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1030</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1186:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Sermon preached at the court at White Hall before the Kings Maiesty, vpon Sunday being the 13. of May 1604. By Anthony Rudd Professor of Diuinitie, and Bishop of Saint Dauids</title>
                  <author>Rudd, Anthony, 1549 or 50-1615.</author>
                  <author>T. W., fl. 1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Field] for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: T.W.</note>
                  <note>On Ps. ci.2.</note>
                  <note>Several pages torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1030:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1030:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE COVRT AT WHITE HALL before the Kings Maieſty, vpon Sunday being the 13. of <hi>May</hi> 1604.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Anthony Rudd Profeſſor of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and Biſhop of Saint Dauids.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1030:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1030:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I had by great meanes obtained a copie of the Sermon follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and read it ouer for mine owne inſtruction, I thought it expedient to publiſh it for the edification of others, who ſhal vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to peruſe it at their beſt leyſure, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it attentiuely, and iudging of it cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1030:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1030:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached at <hi>the Court at White hall</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kings Maieſtie, vpon <hi>Sunday being the</hi> 13. <hi>of May</hi> 1604. By Anthonie Rudd Profeſſor of Diuinitie, and Biſhop of <hi>Saint Dauids.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalme 101. verſe 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I will do wiſely in the perfect way till thou comeſt to me. I will walke in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of mine heart in the midſt of mine houſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text containeth a promiſe of <hi>Dauids</hi> after his entrance into the kingdom of Iſrael. And it conſiſteth of three parts. Firſt, concerning his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1030:4"/>
conuerſation or open cariage, he ſaith, <hi>I will do wiſely in the perfect way.</hi> Secondly, touching his priuate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor or ſecret behauior his words be theſe, <hi>I will walke in the vprightneſſe of mine hart in the midst of mine houſe.</hi> Thirdly, if it be asked, how long <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> will continue in the doing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is here anſwered, <hi>Till thou comest to me:</hi> that is, till thou (ô God) come &amp; cal me away from hence by death; or briefly thus, during my naturall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid in the firſt verſe to ſhew his godly mirth, that he would ſing mercie and iudgement: and nowe here he affirmeth, that he will doe wiſely. So that he promiſeth to be at once both merrie &amp; wiſe. The which in worldly account is iudged and in experience is found to be a matter of great difficultie. Whereupon when <hi>Iobs</hi> ſons gaue themſelues to feaſting,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.5.</note> their father addreſſed himſelfe to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1030:4"/>
for them, doubting ſome vnaduiſed ouerſight in their ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And indeed it was the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar bleſſing of God,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.9.</note> that <hi>Salomon</hi> could taſte of all courtly delights, and yet his wiſedome remained with him.<note place="margin">Deut. 6.10.11.12. &amp; 8.14. &amp;c.</note> For although the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were forewarned, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were once poſſeſſed of cities which they builded not, and houſes furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with all maner of goods which they filled not, and wels which they digged not, and Oliue trees which they planted not, they ſhould beware leaſt they lifted vp their hearts, and forgat the Lord, which brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the land of Aegypt from the houſe of bondage: yet for all that he that hould haue bene vpright,<note place="margin">Deu. 32.15</note> when he waxed ſat ſpurned with the heele, and forſooke God that made him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding not the ſtrong God of his ſaluation. In like ſort, king <hi>Vzziah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chro. 26.5.</note> when as he ſought the Lord, God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1030:5"/>
made him to proſper: but when he was ſtrong,<note place="margin">Ib. verſ. 16.</note> his heart was lift vp to his owne deſtruction. Thus commonly <hi>Eaſe ſlayeth the fooliſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 1.32.</note> 
               <hi>and the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of fooles destroyeth them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Dauid</hi> intendeth euen in his royall proſperitie to do wiſely: know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is an euill thing vnder the Sunne,<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.5.</note> when an errour procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the face of him that ruleth. VVheras on the other ſide, the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the wiſe is the preſeruation of the world;<note place="margin">Sap. 6.24.</note> and a wiſe king is the ſtay of the people. And if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come to ſtrokes, for the defence or honor of the kingdome, better is wiſedome then weapons of warre.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.18</note> Yea verily,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.3</note> an vnwiſe king deſtroieth his people, but where they that be in authoritie are men of vnderſtanding, there the citie proſpereth.</p>
            <p>I haue learned of <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe certaine points of differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce between the wiſe and the vnwiſe. Wherof one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1030:5"/>
appeareth in their looke or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.<note place="margin">Pro. 17.24</note> For <hi>wiſedome is in the face of him that hath vnderſtanding: but the eyes of the foole are in the corners of the world.</hi> So that if you marke the looke of <hi>Shechem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34.2.</note> his eyes be fixed vpon <hi>Dinah.</hi> If you obſerue the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.9</note> you may perceiue that he caſteth the eye of enuie vpon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi> Behold the face of <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 21</note> and loe his eyes be ſetled vpon <hi>Naboths</hi> vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.16</note> Let vs not therefore loue that which is in the world: one of the 3. principals wherof is the luſt of the eyes. And this cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moued <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> to beſeech Almighty God to turn away his eyes from regarding vanity.<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.37.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another difference of the wiſe from the vnwiſe is this,<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.14</note> that <hi>the wiſe mans eyes are in his head, but the foole walketh in darkneſſe:</hi> that is, the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent man foreſeeth things which the vnwiſe cannot for want of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. As for example, prouident <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1030:6"/>
in the firſt entrie into his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">2. Sa. 1.18.</note> hauing his eyes in his head to forecaſt and to preuent future perils, commaunded the children of <hi>Iudah</hi> to be taught to ſhoote, that ſo they might be able to match their enemies the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> in that martiall Art, whether the war ſhold be offenſiue or defenſiue. But the people of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> whoſe Seignoire was very large and fertile, liuing long in peace and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wanting eyes in their head, became careleſſe without miſtruſt, till the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> hauing eſpied both their wealth and their weakneſſe,<note place="margin">Iud. 18.27.</note> ſurpriſed them on a ſudden, and ſmote them with the edge of the ſword, and burnt their citie with fire.</p>
            <p>Among the effects of wiſedome this is one put downe by <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20.5.</note> that whereas <hi>Counſell in the heart of man is like deepe waters, yet a man of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding will draw it out</hi> (by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions &amp; probable coniectures.)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1030:6"/>
So that if <hi>Abſalom</hi> riſe vp early to talk of iuſtice in the gate,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15. 1. ad 7.</note> offering his hand and cheeke to ſuch as come neare vnto him: vndoubtedly a wiſe man will apprehend this to be a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to aſpire to the kingdome.<note place="margin">Gen. 31.2.</note> If <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans</hi> countenance be not toward <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> as it formerly hath bene, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is malice conceiued in his heart.<note place="margin">Iſa. 22.15.16.</note> If my Lord <hi>Shebna</hi> bearing great ſway vnder <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> though he ſee the thrice-potent Emperour of <hi>Aſhur</hi> attempting the conqueſt of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> with an armie iudged inuincible, and yet he do hew himſelfe out a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> wiſe <hi>Hezechiah</hi> will gather thereby, that this is a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing States-man, vnderhand en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining friendſhip with the <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Prince, and being an intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer vnto him, becauſe he would liue ſafely in all chaunges of Church and Common-wealth, Court and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. If two women ſtriue before <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1030:7"/>
about the liuing child,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 3.16. ad fin.</note> and the cauſe proue difficult vpon the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings on both ſides, he will at the length adiudge the child to her in whom he findeth a motherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which cannot abide to heart that bloudie ſpeech of partition: <hi>Nec mihi nec tibi, ſed diuidatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If daunger be imminent for the puniſhment of ſinne,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.3.</note> verily <hi>A prudent man ſeeth the plague and hideth himſelf, but the fooliſh go on ſtill and are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for reprehenſion (which is one of the epiſcopall or paſtorall duties,) <hi>Rebuke not a ſcorner leaſt he hate thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 9.8.</note> 
               <hi>but rebuke a wiſe man, and he will loue thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we conſider the vſe of the tong: behold,<note place="margin">Eccl. 21.26.</note> 
               <hi>The heart of fooles is in their mouth, but the mouth of the wiſe is in their heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we looke into the actions of men, then we ſee,<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.2.</note> that <hi>the heart of a wiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1030:7"/>
man is at his right hand: but the heart of a foole is at his left hand.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently a wiſe man doth all things well, orderly, and iuſtly, whereas the vnwiſe man doth quite the contrarie.</p>
            <p>In the caſe of hearing and credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting other mens ſpeeches:<note place="margin">Pro. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>The fooliſh will beleeue euery thing: but the prudent will conſider his ſteppes:</hi> and ſo be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt flatterie on the one ſide, and ſycophancie on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> wil do wiſely. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? In the perfect way: which is that integritie of ſound religion and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt conuerſation that is preſcribed in the word of God, of which it is ſaid that the lawe of the Lord is perfect.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.</note> And it is ſtiled the perfect lawe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.25.</note> Whereupon we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be chaunged by the renewing of our minds,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> that we may proue what that good, and acceptable, and perfect will of God is, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the holy Scripture, the whole
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1030:8"/>
and euery part whereof is giuen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to conuince, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes. Perfect I ſay in reſpect of knowledge of things neceſſarie to ſaluation: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.9</note> we know now only in part, and prophecie in part. Againe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vnto all good workes in regard of knowledge what ought to be done, but not in reſpect of power and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to performe the ſame. Inſomuch as when our Sauiour biddeth vs to be perfect as our heauenly father is perfect:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48.</note> thoſe words imply onely a like qualitie, but not an equalitie. And when ſome in the Scriptures are ſaid to be perfect,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.6. Philip. 3.15</note> it is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in reſpect of Gods imputation, and not of their owne actions: or in compariſon of others who are ruder in knowledge, or weaker in the faith,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1030:8"/>
or not ſo abundant in good workes: or in regard of their affectionate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and ſound purpoſe of heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hypocriſie, but not of their effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall operation in full practiſe of workes without defect. And in truth one way to perfection hoped for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life, is the knowledge of our imperfection while we continue in this life. But yet ſo, that hauing once knowne what the perfect way or will of God is, we muſt daily march on, or proceed towards perfection in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Gods commandements: the obſeruation whereof is in the iudgement of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.6.</note> our wiſedome and our vnderſtanding in the ſight of all people, who ſeeing our good workes ſhall glorifie God and ſay, <hi>Onely this people is wiſe and of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe Princes are iudged to haue done wiſely in the perfect way of true religion, and the ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1030:9"/>
of God, which haue not onely practiſed the ſame in their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but haue laboured alſo by all meanes to bring all their ſubiects to conformitie therein.<note place="margin">Ioſ. 24.25.</note> As did <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> who made a coueant with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in ioyning God and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple together, by mutuall promiſe of protection from the one, and of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in the other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 15.9 12.13.15.16.</note>Likewiſe king <hi>Aſa</hi> being aſſured of the truth of the religion which he profeſſed, cauſed all his ſubiects to make a couenant by oath to ſeeke the Lord God of their fathers: and they reioyced at the oath, for they ſware with all their hearts. And the penaltie was, that whoſoeuer would not ſeeke the Lord God of Iſrael, ſhould be ſlaine, whether he were ſmall or great, man or woman. Neither did king <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> ſpare his mother <hi>Maachah,</hi> but he depoſed her from her regemie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had made an idol in a groue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1030:9"/>Alſo king <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> went through the people from <hi>Beer-ſheba</hi> to mount <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 19.4</note> and brought them againe to the Lord God of their fathers: that is, from idolatrie to the knowledge and obedience of the true God.</p>
            <p>And at the coronation of young king Ioaſh,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the high Prieſt made a couenant between the Lord and the king and the people, to the end that both the King and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhold maintaine the true worſhip of God, and deſtroy all idolatrie. And moreouer, betweene the King and the people, that he ſhould gouerne, and they obey in the feare of God.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 18.3.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After this king <hi>Hezechiah</hi> purged his country of all monuments of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and ſuperſtition (which was rife in manie places at his firſt entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into the Kingdome) and he turned the Braſen ſerpent into <hi>nehuſhta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (that is, a peece of braſſe) and by writ he ſummoned all the chiefe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1030:10"/>
of his dominions,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 30.5.6.10.11.12.</note> to aſſemble at Ieruſalem, for the celebrating of a moſt ſolemne Paſſeouer; that ſo the hearts of all men might be diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, who were religious and who were ſuperſtitious.</p>
            <p>Not inferiour to him in zeale, if not ſuperiour, was king <hi>Ioſias,</hi> who not only did vprightly in the ſight of the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 34.2</note> walking in the wayes of <hi>Dauid</hi> his father, without bowing to the right hand or to the left, but alſo put downe the Chematims,<note place="margin">2. Reg 23.5.6. &amp;c.</note> and cauſed the altars of <hi>Baalim</hi> to be defaced in his owne ſight, as alſo the carued and molten images to be broken &amp; ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to powder, and then ſtrewed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the graues of them that had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed vnto them: and hauing ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together all the elders of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah and Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Ib verſ. 3.</note> he made a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant before the Lord that they ſhold walke after the Lord, and keepe his commandements with all their harts
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1030:10"/>
and with all their ſoule. And all the people ſtood to the couenant.</p>
            <p>I may not omit <hi>Nehemias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 13 23.24 25.</note> who perceiuing the children of his people to ſpeake halfe in the ſpeech of Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dod, and not perfectly in the Iewiſh language, tooke an oath of them by God, that they ſhould not thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth make anie ſuch entermariages with them of Aſhdod, Ammon, and Moab.</p>
            <p>What would <hi>Artaſhaſht</hi> king of Perſia haue done if he had bene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the law of God,<note place="margin">Ezrae 7 12 14.25.26.</note> ſeeing that being but a profane Prince, yet he gaue authoritie to <hi>Ezra</hi> to reſtore all things according to the word of his God, and to puniſh the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, iudging them without delay, whether it were vnto death, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, confiſcation of goods, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment?</p>
            <p>What zeale for the honour of the God of heauen, and the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1030:11"/>
of the true worſhip of God, would <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> king of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel haue ſhewed, if he had bene trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in the knowledge of the word of God, ſeeing that being onely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuddenly by the greatneſſe of a wonderfull miracle (to praiſe God with his lips, without anie deepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward touch of the heart,) he made a decree in all haſt,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.29.</note> that euery people, nation, and language, which ſpake any blaſphemie againſt the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> ſhould be drawne in peeces, and their houſes ſhould be made a place not to be named in this preſence.</p>
            <p>Verily, <hi>Ioſua, Aſa, Iehoſahat, Ioaſh</hi> during the life of <hi>Iehoiada, Hezechiah, Ioſias,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> aforeſaid, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would nor could in true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome admit the profeſſion and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of any ſauing the right and true religion.<note place="margin">Deut. 22.9.10.11.</note> Knowing that God by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> commaunded, that no man ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1030:11"/>
ſow his vineyard with diuers kinds of ſeedes, nor plow with an oxe and an aſſe together, nor weare a garment of linſey wolſey.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>Eliah</hi> could not endure halting betweene two opinions, but would haue God onely to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, <hi>Baal</hi> being wholly reiected. They of the new Colonies ſent from <hi>Babel, Cuthah, Aua, Hamath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 17.24.25.33.34.</note> and <hi>Sepharuaim,</hi> into the cities of <hi>Samaria</hi> which had bene diſpeopled by the king of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> had indeed no religion, becauſe they had made a compound of two, namely, a true and a falſe. <hi>Zephaniah</hi> could not abide that ſome ſhould ſweare by <hi>Malcham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.5.</note> when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did ſweare by the Lord, or that one ſhould ſweare by both. No man can poſſibly ſerue two maſters,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.24.</note> which be at open variance together.</p>
            <p>What wiſe husbandman hauing ſowne good ſeed in his field,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.24 25.</note> will (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be ſleeping) ſuffer the enemy to ſow tares among the wheate? And
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1030:12"/>
what elſe haue the Ieſuites and Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie men done within this Realme for the ſpace of many yeares? But one watchful King ſitting in the throne of iudgement,<note place="margin">Pro. 20.8.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> will chaſe away all euill with his eyes: and ther-among the he foxes which deſtroy the vines. That it may appeare plainely to the whole world, that he will do wiſely in the perfect way.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, ſee what impediments in the beſt courſes good Princes haue found.<note place="margin">2. Chro. 20.32.33.</note> For though <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> was fully bent to make a perfect reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet the high places were not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, becauſe the people had not hitherto prepared their hearts vnto the God of their fathers. And when <hi>Hezechiah</hi> ſent letters abroad by poſts into euery quarter of the realme to ſummon the people to aſſemble at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chro. 30.10.</note> for the celebrating of a moſt ſolemne paſſe-ouer: they of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> laughed the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1030:12"/>
meſſengers to ſcorne and mocked them.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe <hi>Dauid</hi> for his owne part will do wiſely in the perfect way: and more then that, he will walke, that is, conuerſe or behaue himſelfe. How? In the vprightneſſe of his hart. Where? In the midſt of his houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> (I ſay) will walke in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of his heart, for otherwiſe neither his words nor his works could be acceptable to God. So that all the outward ſemblance of conuerſion and reformation in the old Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Pſal 78.34.35.36.37.</note> was but meere flatterie and diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, becauſe their heart was not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right with God, neither were they faithfull in his couenant. Though <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> intruded himſelf into the Apoſtles companie,<note place="margin">Act 8.21.20.</note> yet he had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part nor fellowſhip in their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe his heart was not right in the ſight of God. <hi>Ananias</hi> alſo and <hi>Sapphira</hi> loſe the reward of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1030:13"/>
if Sathan fil their hearts and moue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lie vnto the holy Ghoſt. If the diuell haue once put treaſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of <hi>Iudas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 13.2. Mat. 26.</note> no good can be expected from him, no not when he ſaluteth and kiſſeth.<note place="margin">Prou. 26.23.24.25.</note> As ſiluer droſſe ouerlaid vpon a potſheard, ſo are bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lippes and an euill heart. He that hateth will counterfeit with his lips, but in his heart he layeth vp deceipt. Though he ſpeake fauorably beleeue him not, for there are ſeuen abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in his heart.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 10.15.16.</note>But on the other ſide, <hi>Iehonadab</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Rechab</hi> was iudged wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be taken vp into the chariot of <hi>Iehu,</hi> and to ſee the zeale which he had for the Lord, becauſe his hart was vpright as <hi>Iehues</hi> was toward him. And <hi>Salomon</hi> at <hi>Gibeon</hi> (where the tabernacle then was) confeſſeth,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 3.6.</note> that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God had ſhewed to his father <hi>Dauid</hi> great mercie, when as he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before him in truth and in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1030:13"/>
and in vprightneſſe of hart with him. Alſo when as God appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Salomon</hi> the ſecond time,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.4.</note> he made vnto him this promiſe, that if he would walke before him in pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart, and in righteouſneſſe as his father had done, then the throne of his kingdome vpon Iſrael ſhold be eſtabliſhed for euer.<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.1.3.</note> When <hi>Hezechiah</hi> receiued a doleful meſſage from God by the mouth of <hi>Iſaias,</hi> ſaying, Put thine houſe in order for thou ſhalt die and not liue: this was his onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that he had walked before God in truth and with a perfect heart. This was <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtay in trouble and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in <hi>Sauls</hi> time,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.10.</note> that his defence was in God, who preſerueth the vpright of heart. They that reade the Pſalmes with attention doe obſerue,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.10.</note> that though many ſorrowes come to the wicked, and God ſhooteth an arrow at them ſuddenly, and their ſtrokes ſhall be at once, yet when iudgement
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1030:14"/>
ſhall returne to iuſtice,<note place="margin">Ib 64.7. Ib. 94.15. Ib. 32.11. Ib. 97.11.</note> then all that are vpright in heart may be ioyfull. For aſſuredly light is ſowne for the righteous, and ioy for the vpright in heart. Light (I ſay) that is, peace, ioy, and perfect felicitie, is ſown for them though they do not preſently reape it; and it is laid vp in ſtore for them, though they do not preſently inioy it. And therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> walked in the vprightneſſe of his heart, and that in the midſt of his houſe.</p>
            <p>Many indeed who pretend holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and honeſtie while they are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlooked by two good tutors, Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and Open place,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.19.</note> afterward giue themſelues to wantonneſſe, to worke all vncleanneſſe, euen with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when as they are couered with the mantle of a darke night, or ſhut vp within the walles of their priuate lodgings, falſly perſwading them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that as they go beyond the knowledge of mortall men, ſo alſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1030:14"/>
the Lord ſhall not ſee, neither will the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> regard it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.7. Pſal. 36.4.2</note> Thus the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man wanting the feare of God before his eyes, and imagining miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe vpon his bed, flattereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his owne conceipt, while his iniquitie is found worthie to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.<note place="margin">Iob. 24.13, 14, 15, 16, 17</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> knew by experience that the murtherer riſeth early to kil the poore and needie: and that theeues dig tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough houſes in the darke which they marked for themſelues in the day time: and that the eye of the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer diſguizing his face, waiteth for the twi-light: and conſequently that the morning is vnto al theſe (and the like) euen as the ſhadow of death. <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi> alſo being brought to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Ezek. 8.12.</note> ſaw that the auncients of the houſe of Iſrael did in the darke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one in the chamber of his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, that which they durſt not do openly and in the day light.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing that many by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1030:15"/>
of nature, euen for common ciuilitie, are aſhamed to act or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute thoſe impieties and iniquities o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly which they commit in ſecret very willingly, how abhominable &amp; damnable is the caſe or ſtate of them which dare and preſume without bluſhing to practiſe hainous offences and outrages in the Sunne-ſhine, and at noone tide?<note place="margin">Gen. 10.9.</note> As <hi>Nimrod</hi> who was prouerbially intituled, <hi>The mightie hunter before the Lord,</hi> becauſe he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to commit crueltie euen in Gods preſence. And of this conſort was <hi>Abſalom</hi> who bluſhed not to ſpread a tent vpon the toppe of the Kings pallace,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.22.</note> and to go in to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers concubines in the ſight of all Iſrael. In this rancke are to be ranged they of whom <hi>Iſay</hi> affirmeth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.9.</note> that the triall of their countenance teſtifieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, yea they declare their ſinnes as Sodome, they hide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. And in reſpect of ſuch ſhameleſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1030:15"/>
dealing, the ſame Prophet challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the people of his age to haue not onely a necke made of an iron ſinew,<note place="margin">Iſa. 48.4.</note> (for obſtinacie) but alſo a brow of braſſe (for impudencie;) and to haue not onely ſet vp the remembrance of their idolatrie behind the doores and poſtes of their houſes,<note place="margin">Ibid. 57.8.7.</note> but alſo openly made their bed of ſpirituall fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon a very high mountaine expoſed to the view of al men. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the great whore that ſitteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon many waters,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.1.4.5.</note> being arrayed in purple and ſcarlet, doth not cloſely hide, but openly beare and ſhew in her very forehead a name written, <hi>A myſterie, great Babylon, the mother of whoredomes and abhominations of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit <hi>Dauid</hi> is ſo farre abſent from tranſgreſſing in publike, that he purpoſeth to walke in the vprightnes of his heart in the midſt of his houſe: knowing that their turning of deuiſes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1030:16"/>
ſhall be eſteemed as the potters clay,<note place="margin">Iſai. 29.16.15.</note> which ſeeke deepe to hide their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels from the Lord: and that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God who knoweth the hearts and reines,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.9.</note> will one day bring euery work vnto iudgement, with euery ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thing whether it be good or euill.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.14.</note> And therefore he will walke in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of his heart in the midſt of his houſe.</p>
            <p>But now how long will <hi>Dauid</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in doing wiſely, and walking vprightly? Till God come and call him away out of this world by death, or in a word, during his naturall life.</p>
            <p>There was hope that <hi>Dauid</hi> would performe this promiſe for the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the kingdome of God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he had formerly giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proofe of his rare patience in his diſtreſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate during the expectancie of the kingdome of Iſrael. For though in that <hi>Interim</hi> of ſundrie yeares atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, after that <hi>Samuel</hi> had annointed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1030:16"/>
him before the crowne fell vnto him by the death of king <hi>Saul,</hi> he ſuſtained many grieuous troubles, inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and daungers, yet he ſtill poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed his ſoule in patience without ſeeking vnlawfull meanes to haſten his owne aduancement, by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of his Soueraigne. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as though <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.3. and 268 9.10.11.12.</note> who deadly purſued him, was twice by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, offered into his hands that he might haue done his pleaſure with him: firſt, in the wilderneſſe of <hi>Engedi:</hi> and ſecondly, in the deſert of <hi>Ziph,</hi> yet he ſpared his life, and did no viol nce to his perſon, leauing him to Gods iudgement, and referring his own cauſe to Gods mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, patiently attending the Lords leyſure till he ſhould vouchſafe to come and put him into the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the kingdome. And now that he hath it, he will perſeuere in a godly courſe to the end, in expectation of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1030:17"/>
the ioyes of heauen.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Dauids</hi> courſe will be cleane contrarie to that of the Apoſtaticall Angels,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note> who abode in the truth but a ſhort time after their creation. Like as afterward <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but a ſmall while in their innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in Paradiſe.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> Alſo <hi>Lots</hi> wife had not farre to go, and yet ſhe locked back before ſhe arriued at the place of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.<note place="margin">Gen 42.15</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> after ſome abode in the king of Aegypts Court learned to ſweare by the life of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſoone turned out of the way which God commaunded them. For while <hi>Moſes</hi> was but fortie dayes abſent from them,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.8.</note> in the mean while they made to themſelues a molten calfe and worſhipped it.<note place="margin">1. Sam 13.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> began well, but he held not out; and ſo for diſobedience he was vtterly reiected.<note place="margin">Hoſ 6.4.</note> The goodneſſe of <hi>Ephraim</hi> was but as a morning cloud,<note place="margin">and 5.</note> and as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dew it went away. <hi>Aſa</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1030:17"/>
of his raigne did that which was good and right in the eyes of the Lord.<note place="margin">2. Chr. 14.2</note> But afterward for feare of <hi>Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> king of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he made a couenant with <hi>Benhadad</hi> king of <hi>Aram:</hi> and impriſoned <hi>Hanani</hi> the Seer becauſe he reproued him for it.<note place="margin">Ib. cap. 16. ver. 1. ad 11</note> And in the end of his life being extreamely pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his feete, he ſought not to the Lord in his diſeaſe, but to the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.<note place="margin">Ib. verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Ioaſh</hi> king of <hi>Iudah</hi> did vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſight of the Lord all the daies of <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the Prieſt:<note place="margin">2. Chr. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but after his death by the aduice of the Peeres of the Realme, (that is, the Princes of <hi>Iudah</hi>) he fell to the practiſe of groſſe idolatrie, and gaue warrant for the execution of <hi>Zechariah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iehoiada,</hi> by ſtoning to death,<note place="margin">Ib verſ. 17. ad 23.</note> for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting againſt thoſe proceedings. <hi>VZ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Ziah</hi> ſought God in the dayes of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 26.</note> who vnderſtood the viſions of God: and when as he ſought the Lord, God made him to proſper. But
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1030:18"/>
in his proſperitie he preſumed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with that which appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not vnto him,<note place="margin">Ib ver. 16. ad. 22.</note> which thing wrought his wofull ouerthrow. O fooliſh Galathians,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.3.</note> after ye haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne in the ſpirit, would ye now be made perfect in the fleſh? Ye recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Paul</hi> as an Angell of God,<note place="margin">Ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. verſ. 14.15.16.</note> yea as Chriſt Ieſus: and ye did once ſo affect him, that if it had bene poſſiible, ye would haue plucked out your owne eyes and haue giuen them vnto him. Is he therefore now become your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, becauſe he tels you the truth? Is it ſo <hi>Demas</hi> that you haue forſaken <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; embraced this preſent world?<note place="margin">2. Tim 4.10.</note> No maruell then if <hi>Himenaeus</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> haue put away a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.19.20.</note> and made ſhip-wrack of faith. Surely theſe went out from vs, but they were not of vs:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. 2.19.</note> for if they had bene of vs, they wold haue remained with vs: becauſe the foundation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſure, and hath this ſeale: The
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1030:18"/>
Lord knoweth who be his.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19</note> Suppoſe (which God forbid) that all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould fall away &amp; ſerue the gods of the Amorites, yet <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe will ſerue the Lorde.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.15</note> Though <hi>Iſrael</hi> play the harlot,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.5.</note> yet let not <hi>Iudah</hi> ſinne. Be it hat the euil one commeth and catcheth away that which is ſowen in his heart, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſeed by the way ſide.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.18. ad 2.24.</note> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit alſo that he which receiueth the ſeed in ſtonie ground, is for want of rooting in himſelf offended as ſoone as tribulation or perſecution cometh becauſe of the word. Put caſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the care of this world and deceitfulneſſe of riches choake the word and make it vnfruitfull in him that receiueth the ſeede among thornes. Yet certainly there be and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will be diuers apt to receiue the ſeed in good ground, who will not ceaſe to beare fruite, and to bring forth ſome an hundred fold, ſome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1030:19"/>
ſixtie fold, ſome thirtie fold. Though many of our Sauiors Diſciples went backe, and walked no more with him after the conference at <hi>Capernaum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.66.67.68.69.</note> yet <hi>Simon Peter</hi> and the reſt of the faithfull companie would not depart from him, becauſe they knew and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that he had the words of eternall life.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.22.</note> And likewiſe they were not ignorant that onely hee which endureth to the end ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            <p>Be conſtant therefore in weldoing, but bragge not of future conſtancie. For without the eſpeciall aſſiſtance of Gods grace,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.33 34.</note> euen <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his preſumption in the morning, will deny his maiſter in the euening.<note place="margin">Apoc. 2.4.</note> And the Angell of the Church of Epheſus will leaue his firſt loue. Yea, without the ſame, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> will ſteppe awry in the matter of <hi>Vriah</hi> the <hi>Hittite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 15.5.</note> and afterward by the prouocation of Satan he will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1030:19"/>
number <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the pride of his hart.<note place="margin">1. Chr. 21.1</note> Likewiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> in his elder yeares will yeeld to the feminine ſexe in their ſeducing vaine.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.5. 2. Chr. 18, 1.</note> Alſo <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> will ioyne himſelfe in affinitie with <hi>Ahab.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 32.25.</note> In like ſort <hi>Hezekiah</hi> will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent for the victory obtained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the inuading <hi>Saneherib,</hi> and will ſhew his treaſures to the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 39.1.2.</note> by way of oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Finally <hi>Ioſiah</hi> will vndertake warre, not conſulting with the Lord, and ſo fight vnfortunately againſt <hi>Pharaoh Necho</hi> at <hi>Megiddo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then theſe dangerous and fearefull examples in others, whereby as in a glaſſe we may obſerue our owne infirmitie,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> let vs pray vnto the God of all grace which hath called vs vnto his eternall glorie by Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, to make vs perfite, confirme, ſtrengthen and ſtabliſh vs, that we may doe wiſely in the perfect way, walking in the vprightneſſe of our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1030:20"/>
hearts in the mids of our houſes, till the time come that we ſhall be called out of this land of our pilgrimage and valley of miſery, and ſo tranſlated to the place of perpetuall and moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie reſt, that when as duſt is returned to earth as it was, and the ſpirite is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to God that gaue it,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.7</note> we may thenceforth for euer be partakers of thoſe heauenly and vnſpeakable ioyes which are purchaſed and prepared for vs by the paſſion and the mediation of our Sauior Chriſt, to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be all honor and glorie both now and for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1030:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
